<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE resume PUBLIC "-//Sean Kelly//DTD Resume 1.2.1//EN"
          "http://xmlresume.sourceforge.net/dtd/resume.dtd">
<!--

This is a resume of Bart Trojanowski

-->
<resume>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>algorithm</keyword>
    <keyword>Apache</keyword>
    <keyword>assembler</keyword>
    <keyword>assembly</keyword>
    <keyword>Athlon</keyword>
    <keyword>bart</keyword>
    <keyword>c</keyword>
    <keyword>c++</keyword>
    <keyword>consulting</keyword>
    <keyword>contract</keyword>
    <keyword>contract programming</keyword>
    <keyword>cross</keyword>
    <keyword>cross-platform</keyword>
    <keyword>debug</keyword>
    <keyword>geek</keyword>
    <keyword>ipsec</keyword>
    <keyword>IP security</keyword>
    <keyword>Java</keyword>
    <keyword>jukie</keyword>
    <keyword>linux</keyword>
    <keyword>logic</keyword>
    <keyword>macos</keyword>
    <keyword>multi threaded</keyword>
    <keyword>multithreaded</keyword>
    <keyword>MySQL</keyword>
    <keyword>object</keyword>
    <keyword>object-oriented</keyword>
    <keyword>Pentium</keyword>
    <keyword>platform</keyword>
    <keyword>porting</keyword>
    <keyword>port</keyword>
    <keyword>programmer</keyword>
    <keyword>real time</keyword>
    <keyword>real-time</keyword>
    <keyword>resume</keyword>
    <keyword>reverse engineering</keyword>
    <keyword>SDK</keyword>
    <keyword>security</keyword>
    <keyword>Smalltalk</keyword>
    <keyword>software development</keyword>
    <keyword>ssh</keyword>
    <keyword>SSL</keyword>
    <keyword>thread</keyword>
    <keyword>UNIX</keyword>
    <keyword>UNIX</keyword>
    <keyword>web</keyword>
    <keyword>x86</keyword>
  </keywords>

  <header>
    <name>
      <firstname>Bart</firstname>
      <surname>Trojanowski</surname>
    </name>
    <address>
      <street>50 Trump Ave.</street>
      <city>Ottawa</city>
      <state>ON</state>
      <zip>K2C 4A4</zip>
      <country>Canada</country>
    </address>
    <contact>
      <phone>613/282-7102</phone>
      <email>bart@jukie.net</email>
      <web>http://www.jukie.net/</web>
    </contact>
  </header>

  <objective>
    <para>I seek direct consulting clients who require custom software development. Services are provided for clients worldwide. I strive to achieve quality, accuracy, performance and maintainability in the products I write.
    </para>
  </objective>

    <skillarea>
      <title>Skills</title>
      <skillset>
	<title>General Experience</title>
	  <skill>Fluent in C, C++, Java, JavaScript, Perl, PHP, Intel and Motorola assembly, SmallTalk, SQL, Pascal, and BASIC.</skill>
	  <skill>Experienced in many operating systems such as: Linux, Solaris, FreeBSD, Windows 2k/NT/98, DOS, MacOS.</skill>
	  <skill>Very strong problem solving skills.</skill>
	  <skill>Proficient in multi-threaded and real-time application design and development.</skill>
	  <skill>Designed various cross-platform libraries.</skill>
	  <skill>Theoretical and applied understanding of vast network systems, protocols and concepts.</skill>
	  <skill>Performed development, testing, benchmarking, and debugging many networking and multi-threaded/multi-processor application using Linux tools.</skill>
	  <skill>Exposure in debugging and optimizing gcc and gdb, of the GNU tool chain, for a custom built ARC processor.</skill>
	  <skill>Familiar with X application development using GTK+ libraries.</skill>
	  <skill>Working knowledge of Microsoft Access, DBase IV, and mySQL at both environment and programming levels.</skill>
	  <skill>Familiarity with countless desktop publishing, productivity and scientific software for various platforms.</skill>
      </skillset>
      <skillset>
	<title>Networking</title>
	  <skill>Berkeley sockets (UNIX networking)</skill>
          <skill>Winsock 1/2 (Windows networking)</skill>
	  <skill>Network security (firewalls, proxy servers, etc.)</skill>
	  <skill>TCP, UDP, ICMP, Multicast internals</skill>
	  <skill>Ethernet, IP and PPP connectivity</skill>
	  <skill>Routing (mrouted, RIP, BGP) and switching</skill>
	  <skill>Low-level FTP, HTTP, Telnet, POP3, SMTP, SAMBA</skill>
	  <skill>Development of IPSec and ISAKMP/IKE protocols</skill>
	  <skill>SSH, SSL, NFS</skill>
	  <skill>Internet/Intranet</skill>
	  <skill>DVB and MPEG standards</skill>
      </skillset>
      <skillset>
	<title>Kernel/Embedded</title>
	  <skill>Extensive knowledge of Linux kernel internals; worked on various optimization projects for the Linux kernel.</skill>
	  <skill>In depth understanding of Linux boot sequence; used to design custom Linux distribution for use in embedded applications.</skill>
	  <skill>Expert in debugging, modifying, porting, and optimization of Linux kernel sources.</skill>
	  <skill>Experienced in embedded development under Linux and pSOS operating systems.</skill>
	  <skill>Design and implementation knowledge for real-time systems.</skill>
          <skill>Understanding of Solaris and NT driver development.</skill>
      </skillset>
    </skillarea>

  <history>
    <job>
      <jobtitle>Software Developer</jobtitle>
      <employer>SOMA Networks</employer>
      <period>
	<from>
	  <date>
	    <month>November</month>
	    <year>2001</year>
	  </date>
	</from>
	<to>
	  <date>
	    <month>Present</month>
	    <year></year>
	  </date>
	</to>
      </period>
      <description>
	<para>designed, implemented, and responsible for a set of drivers handling host to radio communication and configuration, via PCI bus.  the target platforms of said drivers are arm-linux and x86-linux.
	</para>
      </description>
    </job>

    <job>
      <jobtitle>Software Developer</jobtitle>
      <employer>Chrysalis-ITS</employer>
      <period>
	<from>
	  <date>
	    <month>January</month>
	    <year>2000</year>
	  </date>
	</from>
	<to>
	  <date>
	    <month>August</month>
	    <year>2001</year>
	  </date>
	</to>
      </period>
      <description>
	<para>designed, implemented, and responsible for maintenance of a cross platform (Linux/FreeBSD) driver and debug tools for a PCI device; helped in porting it to WinNT and Solaris; designed and implemented an automated testing environment for the PCI device; involved in porting a kernel IPSec implementation to use a hardware accelerator; written various kernel modules to exercise the Chrysalis-ITS hardware; also, worked on various internal tools used by the firmware developers; provided Linux tutelage to other project developers; as a background task maintained a project CVS/NFS server for various developers. 
	</para>
      </description>
    </job>

    <job>
      <jobtitle>Software Specialist</jobtitle>
      <employer>International Datacasting Corporation</employer>
      <period>
	<from>
	  <date>
	    <month>May</month>
	    <year>1998</year>
	  </date>
	</from>
	<to>
	  <date>
	    <month>January</month>
	    <year>2000</year>
	  </date>
	</to>
      </period>
      <description>
	<para>provide support and maintain the Java 'Superflex Status &amp; Control' application (as described below); researched the needed tools and support software, in part designed, and developed the majority of the firmware to drive the next generation Superflex product; firmware is written in C++, taking advantage of POSIX threads, and runs on Linux; was in charge of reducing a commercial Linux install down to 8 MB to fit on a flash disk.
	</para>
	<para>extensively involved in design of the firmware and control protocol specification for the new data satellite receiver; solely responsible for research of technologies and development of the firmware; the product uses off the shelf and proprietary products that must be integrated; firmware allows for easy exchange of current hardware for other that are not yet available.
        </para>
      </description>
    </job>

    <job>
      <jobtitle>Software Developer</jobtitle>
      <employer>International Datacasting Corporation</employer>
      <period>
	<from>
	  <date>
	    <month>Aug</month>
	    <year>1997</year>
	  </date>
	</from>
	<to>
	  <date>
	    <month>April</month>
	    <year>1998</year>
	  </date>
	</to>
      </period>
      <description>
        <para>designed and implemented a Java application GUI named 'Status &amp; Control' for the Superflex line of satellite receivers; helped in the effort of debugging pSOS-based firmware, written in C++, that was configured by the GUI; as a result became very comfortable with switching between Java and C++; aided in the debugging efforts of a QNX system control software used to remotely control receivers; maintained transmit-side modulator software; as a side project built and maintained a Linux routing &amp; gatewaying server that ran a mail spooler, a local DNS and other services.
        </para>
      </description>
    </job>

    <job>
      <jobtitle>Software Developer / Assistant Project Manager</jobtitle>
      <employer>Evergreen Wildfire Systems</employer>
      <period>
	<from>
	  <date>
	    <month>September</month>
	    <year>1996</year>
	  </date>
	</from>
	<to>
	  <date>
	    <month>August</month>
	    <year>1997</year>
	  </date>
	</to>
      </period>
      <description>
	<para>involved in the development of Sparrow GIS software; duties range from constructing graphing and charting facilities, to user interface design and debugging code for Sparrow, a program which visually represents geographical statistics retrieved from relational databases;
	</para>
        <para>involved in supervising and development of many projects including "Parks Fire Web" an Intranet &amp; Internet solution to distributing public and internal forest fire information amongst its institutions;
	</para>
      </description>
    </job>

    <job>
      <jobtitle>Software Developer / Consultant</jobtitle>
      <employer>Parks Canada</employer>
      <period>
	<from>
	  <date>
	    <month>May</month>
	    <year>1995</year>
	  </date>
	</from>
	<to>
	  <date>
	    <month>August</month>
	    <year>1996</year>
	  </date>
	</to>
      </period>
      <description>
	<para>participated in the development of the fire management system currently in use by National Parks of Canada; duties included the design a GUI to provide remote database access functions &amp; greater ease of use; after project completion involved in updating this system to current client requirements, adding functionality to the existing application;
	</para>
      </description>
    </job>

    <job>
      <jobtitle>Software Developer/Consultant</jobtitle>
      <employer>Datacast Communications</employer>
      <period>
	<from>
	  <date>
	    <month>September</month>
	    <year>1995</year>
	  </date>
	</from>
	<to>
	  <date>
	    <month>April</month>
	    <year>1996</year>
	  </date>
	</to>
      </period>
      <description>
	<para>while on the project entitled "Newspapers for the blind" assisted the visually challenged in setting up VBI equipment in home in order to receive electronic papers; participated in a team environment to develop a WWW server, for Smart Communities, that mimicking Yellow Pages but in electronic form;
	</para>
      </description>
    </job>

    <job>
      <jobtitle>Junior Software Developer</jobtitle>
      <employer>Telesat Canada</employer>
      <period>
	<from>
	  <date>
	    <month>June</month>
	    <year>1994</year>
	  </date>
	</from>
	<to>
	  <date>
	    <month>August</month>
	    <year>1994</year>
	  </date>
	</to>
      </period>
      <description>
	<para>high school summer Co-op; placed, at personal request; briefly introduced to networking on IBM/9000, the Virtual Machine environment and UNIX architectures; tasks involved developing database entry sheets for personnel, payroll and security data on the VM; also developed helper applications using the C programming language under UNIX;
	</para>
      </description>
    </job>

  </history>



  <academics>
    <degrees>
      <degree>
	<level>Bachelor of Science</level>
	<subject>Computer Science with Software Option</subject>
	<date>
	  <month>May</month>
	  <year>1999</year>
	</date>
	<institution>Carleton University</institution>
        <annotation>
          <para>Five year Co-op program.  Degree awarded with <emphasis>Highest Honours</emphasis> standing. 
          </para>
          <para>Studies concentrated on: Computer Networking and Cryptography
, Operating Systems &amp; Real-time Systems, Object Oriented Programming, Artificial Intelligence, Computer Graphics &amp; Simulations, and Database Development.
          </para>
        </annotation>
      </degree>
    </degrees>

    <degrees>
      <degree>
	<level>Ontario Academic Credits Diploma</level>
	<subject>High School</subject>
	<date>
	  <month>May</month>
	  <year>1994</year>
	</date>
	<institution>Sir Wilfrid Laurier Secondary School</institution>
        <annotation>
          <para>Diploma awarded with <emphasis>Honours</emphasis> standing.
          </para>
        </annotation>
      </degree>
    </degrees>

  </academics>


  <misc>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Open Source Projects</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>maintains window manager wmii-lua; see <link>http://github.com/bartman/wmii-lua</link>.</para>
    <para>contributed to Debian port to AMD64 architecture (AMD Opteron chip); see <link>http://www.jukie.net/~bart/debian/amd64/</link>.</para>
    <para>involved in redesign efforts of KLIPS (kernel part of the IPSec implementation for Linux); my involvement lies in the development of a kernel-space crypto library; see: <link>http://www.jukie.net/~bart/linux-ipsec</link>.</para>
    <para>developed an elf signing utility which uses the GnuPG engine for digitally signing elf executables; see: <link>http://elfsign.sourceforge.net</link>.</para>
    <para>... and much, much more; see <link>https://www.ohloh.net/accounts/bartman</link> and <link>http://github.com/bartman</link></para>
  </misc>

</resume>
<!--
#vim: et ts=2 sw=2
-->
